The public debate about architecture
النقاش العام حول فن العمارة
quite often just stays on contemplating the final result,
غالباً ما ينصب على التفكير في النتيجة النهائية
the architectural object.
نوع الكائن المعماري
Is the latest tower in London
هل البرج الأخير في لندن
a gherkin or a sausage
يبدو كخيارة ، أم قطعة من النقانق
or a sex tool?
أم أداة جنسية؟
So recently, we asked ourselves
لذلك مؤخراً سألنا أنفسنا
if we could invent a format
هل باستطاعتنا إبتكار شكل
that could actually tell the stories behind the projects,
يمكن ان يقوم في الواقع برواية القصص وراء المشاريع
maybe combining images and drawings and words
ربما يقوم بالجمع بين الصور والرسومات والكلمات
to actually sort of tell stories about architecture.
ليتمكن من رواية القصص حول الهندسة المعمارية
And we discovered that we didn't have to invent it,
ومن ثم اكتشفنا أننا لم نكن نحتاج لنخترع ذلك
it already existed in the form of a comic book.
إنه موجود بالفعل في شكل كتاب فكاهي
So we basically copied the format of the comic book
لذلك قمنا أساساً بنسخ محتوى الكتاب الفكاهي
to actually tell the stories of behind the scenes,
وبذلك نستطيع رواية القصص خلف الكواليس
how our projects actually evolve through adaptation
كيف في الحقيقة مشاريعنا تتطور عبر التكيف
and improvisation.
والإرتجال
Sort of through the turmoil and the opportunities
من خلال نوع من الاضطراب والفرص
and the incidents of the real world.
وأحداث العالم الحقيقية
We call this comic book "Yes is More,"
قمنا بتسمية هذا الكتاب الفكاهي ب "بلى هو المزيد"
which is obviously a sort of evolution of the ideas of some of our heroes.
والذي واضح أنه نوع من تطور الأفكار لبعض أبطالنا
In this case it's Mies van der Rohe's Less is More.
والذي هو في هذه الحالة كتاب "الأقل هو المزيد" لميس فان دير روه
He triggered the modernist revolution.
الذي أشعل شرارة الثورة الحداثية
After him followed the post-modern counter-revolution,
ومن بعده في مرحلة الثورة المضادة للثورة الحديثة
Robert Venturi saying, "Less is a bore."
روبرت فينتوري قال "الأقل هو الملل"
After him, Philip Johnson sort of introduced
ومن بعده قدم فيليب جونسن نوعاً من
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
you could say promiscuity, or at least openness
يمكنك ان تقول المجون ، على الأقل الإنفتاح
to new ideas with, "I am a whore."
للأفكار الجديدة ب "انا عاهرة"
Recently, Obama has introduced optimism
ومؤخراً قدم أوباما التفاؤل
at a sort of time of global financial crisis.
في خضم الأزمة المالية العالمية
And what we'd like to say with "Yes is More"
وما نريد قوله ب "بلى هو المزيد"
is basically trying to question this idea
هو في الأساس محاولة لوضع هذه الفكرة في شكل سؤال
that the architectural avant-garde is almost always negatively defined,
أن التطلع والتقدمية المعمارية دائما ما يكون تعريفها سلبياً
as who or what we are against.
كـ "من" أو "ماذا" نحن ضده
The cliche of the radical architect
إبتذال المعمارية الراديكالية
is the sort of angry young man rebelling against the establishment.
هونوع من غضب الشاب المنتقض ضد المؤسسة
Or this idea of the misunderstood genius,
أو أن هذه فكرة عبقرية يساء فهمها ،
frustrated that the world doesn't fit in with his or her ideas.
أحس أو أحست بالإحباط من أن العالم لا يتناسب مع أفكاره أو أفكارها
Rather than revolution, we're much more interested in evolution,
فبدلاً عن الثورة ، نحن مهتمون أكثر بالتطور
this idea that things gradually evolve
وبفكرة أن الأمور تتطور بالتدريج
by adapting and improvising
من خلال التكيف والأرتجال
to the changes of the world.
وصولاً إلى إحداث التغييرات في العالم
In fact, I actually think that Darwin is one of the people
في الواقع، أنا أعتقد ان داروين هو واحد من الناس
who best explains our design process.
الذين قاموا بشرح عملية تصميمنا بأفضل طريقة
His famous evolutionary tree
شجرته للتطور المشهورة
could almost be a diagram of the way we work.
يمكنها ان تصبح مخططاً للطريقة التي نعمل بها
As you can see, a project evolves through
فكما يمكنكم أن تروا ، فإن المشروع يتطور عبر
a series of generations of design meetings.
سلسلة من الأجيال لإجتماعات التصميم
At each meeting, there's way too many ideas.
وفي كل لقاء هنالك العديد من الأفكار
Only the best ones can survive.
فقط الجيدة منها التي يتم الإبقاء عليها
And through a process of architectural selection,
ومن خلال عملية الإختيار المعماري
we might choose a really beautiful model
قد نقوم بإختيار نموذج جميل فعلاً
or we might have a very functional model.
أو قد نقوم بإختيار نموذج عملي للغاية
We mate them. They have sort of mutant offspring.
ونقوم بجمعهما معاً ، وبذلك نحصل على سلالة لها نوع من الطفرة
And through these sort of generations of design meetings
ومن خلال هذه الأجيال من لقاءات التصميم
we arrive at a design.
نصل إلى تصميم
A very literal way of showing it is a project we did
أكثر طريقة لوصف ذلك حرفياً، هو مشروع قمنا به
for a library and a hotel in Copenhagen.
لمكتبة وفندق في كوبنهاغن
The design process was really tough,
كانت عملية التصميم صعبة ومرهقة فعلاً
almost like a struggle for survival,
تقريبا" كالكفاح من أجل البقاء
but gradually an idea evolved:
ولكن تدريجياً تطورت الفكرة
this sort of idea of a rational tower
هذا النوع من الافكار حول بناء برج ذكي أو يتسم بالإدراك
that melts together with the surrounding city,
يندمج بسهولة مع المدينة المحيطة به
sort of expanding the public space onto what we refer to as
نوع من التوسع في الفضاء العام لما نطلق عليه
a Scandinavian version of the Spanish Steps in Rome,
النسخة الاسكندنافية للعتبات الاسبانية في روما
but sort of public on the outside, as well as on the inside,
عام نوعاً ما من الخارج كما هو الحال بالداخل
with the library.
مع المكتبة
But Darwin doesn't only explain the evolution of a single idea.
لكن داروين لا يوضح فقط التطور لفكرة مفردة
As you can see, sometimes a subspecies branches off.
فكما يمكنكم أن تشاهدوا ، بعض الأحيان السلالة تتفرع
And quite often we sit in a design meeting
وكثيراً ما كنا نجلس في إجتماع التصميم
and we discover that there is this great idea.
ونكتشف أن هنالك فكرة عظيمة
It doesn't really work in this context.
ولكنها لا تتوائم مع هذا السياق
But for another client in another culture,
ولكن لزبون آخر من ثقافة أخرى
it could really be the right answer to a different question.
فإنها يمكن ان تكون فعلاً الإجابة الصحيحة لسؤال مختلف
So as a result, we never throw anything out.
نتيجة لذلك، لم نقم برمي أي شي أو التخلص منه
We keep our office almost like an archive
بل جعلنا مكتبنا تقريباً كأرشيف
of architectural biodiversity.
للتنوع البيولوجي المعماري
You never know when you might need it.
لأنك لا تعرف أبداً متى تكون بحاجة إليها
And what I'd like to do now, in an act of
وما أريد القيام به الآن هو عبارة عن
warp-speed storytelling,
رواية لقصة سريعة
is tell the story of how two projects evolved
للحديث عن كيفية تطور إثنين من المشاريع
by adapting and improvising
عبر التكيف والإرتجال
to the happenstance of the world.
وصولاً إلى المصادفة في العالم
The first story starts last year when we went to Shanghai
القصة الأولى بدأت عندما ذهبنا العام الماضي إلى شانغهاي
to do the competition for the Danish
للمشاركة في الجناح الدنماركي
National Pavilion for the World Expo in 2010.
للمعرض العالمي في 2010
And we saw this guy, Haibao.
ورأينا هذا الشخص الذي يدعى ، هايباو
He's the mascot of the expo,
لقد كان تميمة المعرض
and he looks strangely familiar.
وكان يبدو مألوفاً بصورة غريبة
In fact he looked like a building we had designed
في الحقيقة كان يبدو كالمبنى الذي صممناه
for a hotel in the north of Sweden.
للفندق في شمال السويد
When we submitted it for the Swedish competition we thought
وعندما نافسنا به في السويد
it was a really cool scheme, but it didn't exactly
كان يبدو أنه مشروع رائع، لكنه في الحقيقة
look like something from the north of Sweden.
لم يبد انه يشبه شيئاً من شمال السويد
The Swedish jury didn't think so either. So we lost.
والمحكم السويدي أيضاً لم يقتنع بذلك، لذلك خسرنا
But then we had a meeting with a Chinese businessman
لكن كان لدينا إجتماع مع رجل أعمال صيني
who saw our design and said,
قام برؤية تصاميمنا وعلق قائلاً:
"Wow, that's the Chinese character for the word 'people.'"
"ياللروعة، هذا يمثل الرمز الصيني لكلمة الشعب"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, apparently this is how you write "people,"
يبدو أن هذه هي الطريقة التي تكتب بها كلمة "الشعب"
as in the People's Republic of China.
في جمهورية الصين الشعبية
We even double checked.
لم نقم بالتأكد مرتين
And at the same time, we got invited to exhibit
وفي نفس الوقت، دعينا إلى معرض
at the Shanghai Creative Industry Week.
في أسبوع شانغهاي للصناعة الخلاقة
So we thought like, this is too much of an opportunity,
ففكرنا ، هذه أكثر من مجرد فرصة
so we hired a feng shui master.
وقمنا بتعيين أستاذ في الفينغ شوي "فلسفة صينية تركز على فن التناغم مع الفضاء المحيط"
We scaled the building up three times to Chinese proportions,
وقمنا بإعادة القياسات ثلاث مرات لتتناسب و النسب الصينية
and went to China.
ومن ثم ذهبنا إلى الصين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the People's Building, as we called it.
إذا مبنى الشعب، كما أطلقنا عليه
This is our two interpreters, sort of reading the architecture.
تبعاً لمترجمتينا الفوريين الإثنتين، نوع من قراءة فن العمارة
It went on the cover of the Wen Wei Po newspaper,
وأصبحت قصة الغلاف لصحيفة وين وي بو
which got Mr. Liangyu Chen, the mayor of Shanghai,
مما دعى عمدة شانغهاي، السيد ليانغ يو تشين
to visit the exhibition.
لزيارة المعرض
And we had the chance to explain the project.
وحصلنا على الفرصة لشرح المشروع
And he said, "Shanghai is the city in the world
ومن ثم قال "شانغهاي هي أكثر مدينة في العالم
with most skyscrapers,"
تحتوي على ناطحات سحاب"
but to him it was as if the connection to the roots had been cut over.
لكن بالنسبة إليه كان الموضوع عبارة عن العودة والإتصال مع الجذور
And with the People's Building, he saw an architecture
ومع مبنى الشعب الذي رآه ، رأى فيه
that could bridge the gap between the ancient wisdom of China
الجسر الذي يعبر الهوة ما بين حكمة الصين القديمة
and the progressive future of China.
والمستقبل المتنامي للصين
So we obviously profoundly agreed with him.
لذا كنا متفقين معه تماماً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Unfortunately, Mr. Chen is now in prison for corruption.
لسوء الحظ ، فإن السيد تشين الآن في السجن لتهم تتعلق بالفساد المالي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But like I said, Haibao looked very familiar,
لكن كما قلت ، فإن تميمة المعرض "هايباو" بدا مشابهة جداً
because he is actually the Chinese character for "people."
لأنه هو حقيقة الرمز الصيني لكلمة "الشعب"
And they chose this mascot because
وقد قامو بإختياره كتميمة لأن
the theme of the expo is "Better City, Better Life."
لأن شعار المعرض كان "مدينة أفضل، حياة أفضل"
Sustainability.
بطريقة مستدامة
And we thought, sustainability has grown into being
واعتقدنا أن الإستدامة غدت حيزاً في الوجود
this sort of neo-Protestant idea
لتصبح هذا النوع من الأفكار المحافظة الجديدة
that it has to hurt in order to do good.
لفعل الأشياء بطريقة سيئة وصولاً إلى فعلها بطريقة جيدة
You know, you're not supposed to take long, warm showers.
كما تعلمون ، إنه يبدو كأنه ليس من المفترض أن تأخذ حماماً دافئاً وطويلاً
You're not supposed to fly on holidays because it's bad for the environment.
ليس من المحبذ أن تسافر في العطل ، لأنه سئ للبيئة
Gradually, you get this idea that sustainable life
تدريجياً تصل للفكرة بأن الحياة المستدامة
is less fun than normal life.
ليست ممتعة بقدر حياتنا العادية
So we thought that maybe it could be interesting to focus on examples
لذلك فكرنا بأنه قد يكون من الممتع التركيز على أمثلة
where a sustainable city
حيث أن المدينة المستدامة
actually increases the quality of life.
ستكون قادرة حقيقة على زيادة جودة الحياة
We also asked ourselves, what could Denmark possibly show China
أيضاً سألنا انفسنا ، ماذا الذي يمكن للدنمارك أن تقدمه للصين
that would be relevant?
بحيث يكون ذا صلة؟
You know, it's one of the biggest countries in the world, one of the smallest.
كما تعلمون ، أنها واحدة من أكبر دول العالم تقابلها واحدة من أصغرها
China symbolized by the dragon.
الصين تمثل بالتنين
Denmark, we have a national bird, the swan.
بينما الدنمارك تتمثل بطائرها الوطني ، البجعة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
China has many great poets,
للصين العديد من الشعراء العظام
but we discovered that in the People's Republic
لكننا اكتشفنا انه في الجمهورية الشعبية
public school curriculum,
المناهج التعليمية المدرسية
they have three fairy tales by An Tu Sheng,
تحتوي على ثلاث حكايات بقلم ان تو شونغ
or Hans Christian Anderson, as we call him.
أو هانز كريستيان أندرسن ، كما أطلقنا عليه
So that means that all 1.3 billion Chinese
هذا يعني أن 1.3 مليار صيني
have grown up with "The Emperor's New Clothes,"
قد ترعرعوا مع قصص ك "ملابس الامبراطور الجديدة"
"The Matchstick Girl" and "The Little Mermaid."
"فتاة عود الثقاب" ، و "الحورية الصغيرة"
It's almost like a fragment of Danish culture
والتي تقريباً تمثل جزءاً من الثقافة الدنماركية
integrated into Chinese culture.
أدمجت في الثقافة الصينية
The biggest tourist attraction in China is the Great Wall.
المعلم السياحي الجاذب الأكبر بالصين هو سور الصين العظيم
The Great Wall is the only thing that can be seen from the moon.
سور الصين العظيم هو الشئ الوحيد على الأرض الذي يمكن رؤيته من على القمر
The big tourist attraction in Denmark is The Little Mermaid.
بينما معلم الدنمارك الأكبر الجاذب سياحياً هو حورية البحر الصغيرة
That can actually hardly be seen from the canal tours.
والتي تتم رؤيتها بشق الأنفس في الجولات علي القنال
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it sort of shows the difference between these two cities.
إنه نوع من المقاربة والعرض للإختلافات مابين هاتين المدينتين
Copenhagen, Shanghai,
كوبنهاغن ، وشنغهاي
modern, European.
مدينة حديثة، وأخرى ذات طابع اوروبي
But then we looked at recent urban development,
ومن ثم تمعنا في التنمية الحضرية الحالية
and we noticed that this is like a Shanghai street,
ولاحظنا أن هذا يشبه شوارع شنغهاي
30 years ago. All bikes, no cars.
قبل ثلاثين عاماً مضت. مليئة بالدراجات ولا تحتوي على سيارات
This is how it looks today; all traffic jam.
وهذا ما تبدو عليه اليوم، مزدحمة مرورياً بالكامل
Bicycles have become forbidden many places.
وأضحت الدراجات ممنوعة في العديد من الأماكن
Meanwhile, in Copenhagen we're actually expanding the bicycle lanes.
بينما في الوقت نفسه في كوبنهاغن نقوم في الحقيقة بتوسيع ممرات الدراجات
A third of all the people commute by bike.
ثلث السكان يستخدمون الدراجات في التنقل
We have a free system of bicycles called the City Bike
لدينا نظام مجاني للدراجات يسمي دراجة المدينة
that you can borrow if you visit the city.
بحيث يمكنك الحصول على دراجة على سبيل الاقتراض إذا قمتم بزيارة المدينة
So we thought, why don't we reintroduce the bicycle in China?
ومن ثم فكرنا ، لماذا لا نعيد انتاج مفهوم الدراجة في الصين
We donate 1,000 bikes to Shanghai.
فقمنا بالتبرع ب 1000 دراجة لشانغهاي
So if you come to the expo, go straight to the Danish pavilion,
إذا تمكنتم من زيارة المعرض، اتجهوا مباشرة إلى الجناح الدنماركي
get a Danish bike, and then continue on that to visit the other pavilions.
ومن ثم احصلوا على دراجة دنماركية ، وواصلوا قيادتها الى بقية أجنحة المعرض
Like I said, Shanghai and Copenhagen are both port cities,
كما قلت ، شانغهاي وكوبنهاغن ميناءان
but in Copenhagen the water has gotten so clean
لكن في كوبنهاغن المياه نظيفة جداً
that you can actually swim in it.
بحيث يمكنك فعلاً أن تسبح عبرها
One of the first projects we ever did
واحد من أول المشروعات التي قمنا بها
was the harbor bath in Copenhagen,
كان عبارة عن حوض استحمام المرفأ
sort of continuing the public realm into the water.
نوع من تواصل الملكية العامة وصولاَ للمياه
So we thought that these expos quite often have a lot of
اعتقدنا أن هذه المعارض غالباً ما تحوي الكثير
state financed propaganda,
من الدعاية الممولة من قبل الدولة
images, statements, but no real experience.
صور ، بيانات ، لكن لا خبرة حقيقية
So just like with a bike, we don't talk about it.
فمع الدراجة ، لم نتحدث عنها
You can try it.
يمكنك ان تقوم بتجربتها
Like with the water, instead of talking about it,
كما في الحالة مع موضوع المياه، بدلاً عن التحدث عنها
we're going to sail a million liters of harbor water
سنقوم بالابحار ب مليون ليتر من مياه المرفأ
from Copenhagen to Shanghai,
من كوبنهاغن الى شانغهاي
so the Chinese who have the courage can actually dive in
حيث سيتمكن الصينيون الذين لديهم الشجاعة من الغطس داخلها
and feel how clean it is.
والاحساس بمدى نظافتها
This is where people normally object that it doesn't sound very sustainable
هذه غاية الناس عادة انها لا تبدوا بهذه الاستدامة
to sail water from Copenhagen to China.
للإبحار بمياه المرفأ من كوبنهاغن الى الدنمارك
But in fact, the container ships go
حيث أنه في الحقيقة سفينة الحاويات
full of goods from China to Denmark,
كانت محملة بالأساس ببضائع من الصين للدنمارك
and then they sail empty back.
ومن ثم أبحرت فارغة عائدة الى شانغهاي
So quite often you load water for ballast.
ومن ثم تمكنا من شحن المياه كثقل للموازنة
So we can actually hitch a ride for free.
لذلك نوعاً ما ، تمكنا في الحقيقة من الركوب مجاناً
And in the middle of this sort of harbor bath,
ووسط هذا النوع من مياه حوض استحمام المرفأ
we're actually going to put the actual Little Mermaid.
سنقوم حقيقة بوضع حورية البحر الصغيرة الحقيقية
So the real Mermaid, the real water, and the real bikes.
إذاً إنها الحورية الحقيقية، المياه الحقيقية، والدراجات الحقيقية
And when she's gone, we're going to invite
وحالما تذهب سنقوم بدعوة
a Chinese artist to reinterpret her.
فنان صيني ليفسرها
The architecture of the pavilion is this sort of loop
معمارية الجناح كانت نوعاً من الحلقة
of exhibition and bikes.
مابين المعرض والدراجات
When you go to the exhibition, you'll see the Mermaid and the pool.
عندما تذهبون الى المعرض سترون الحورية والحوض
You'll walk around, start looking for a bicycle on the roof,
ستدورون من حوله، وتبدأون بالبحث عن دراجة من على السقف
jump on your ride and then continue out into the rest of the expo.
وتمتطيها في طريقك لمواصلة التجول في باقي المعرض
So when we actually won the competition
لذلك عندما فزنا بالمنافسة
we had to do an exhibition in China explaining the project.
كان علينا ان نقوم بعمل معرض بالصين لشرح المشروع
And to our surprise we got one of our boards back
ولدهشتنا عادت احدى مخططاتنا
with corrections from the Chinese state censorship.
مع تعديلات من الرقابة الحكومية للصين
The first thing, the China map missed Taiwan.
الشئ الأول ، هو ان خريطة الصين لم تكن تحتوي على تايوان
It's a very serious political issue in China. We will add on.
إنه موضوع سياسي غاية في الحساسية في الصين ، سنقوم باضافتها
The second thing, we had compared the swan to the dragon,
الشئ الثاني، كنا قد قارنا البجعة بالنسبة للتنين
and then the Chinese state said,
ومن قالت الحكومة الصينية
"Suggest change to panda."
" يقترح تغييرها الي الباندا"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, when it came out in Denmark that we were actually going to
لذلك حينما عادت الى الدنمارك حيث كنا في الحقيقة في طريقنا
move our national monument,
لنقل نصبنا التذكاري
the National People's Party sort of rebelled against it.
حزب الشعب القومي نوعاً ما تمرد ضدها
They tried to pass a law against moving the Mermaid.
حاولوا تمرير قانون يعارض نقل الحورية
So for the first time, I got invited to speak at the National Parliament.
لذلك للمرة الأولى ، دعيت للتحدث أمام البرلمان الوطني
It was kind of interesting because in the morning, from 9 to 11,
كانت نوعاً ما ممتعة لانها كانت من التاسعة إلى الحادية عشرة صباحاً
they were discussing the bailout package --
حين كانوا يناقشون خطة للإنقاذ
how many billions to invest in saving the Danish economy.
وكيف أن المليارات ستستثمر لانقاذ الاقتصاد الدنماركي
And then at 11 o'clock they stopped talking about these little issues.
وعند الحادية عشرة، توقفوا عن مناقشة هذه المواضيع الصغيرة
And then from 11 to 1,
ومن الحادية عشرة الى الواحدة
they were debating whether or not to send the Mermaid to China.
كانوا يتناقشون حول ارسال الحورية من عدمه إلى الصين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But to conclude, if you want to see the Mermaid from May to December
لكن في الختام ، اذا أردت ان ترى حورية البحر من مايو الى ديسمبر
next year, don't come to Copenhagen,
في السنة القادمة ، فلا تأتي الى كوبنهاغن
because she's going to be in Shanghai.
لأنها ستكون في شانغهاي ذلك الوقت
If you do come to Copenhagen,
إذا تمكنت من الحضور الى كوبنهاغن
you will probably see an installation by Ai Weiwei, the Chinese artist.
سترى غالباً نصباً من ابداع الفنان الصيني إي ويوي
But if the Chinese government intervenes, it might even be a panda.
لكن اذا تدخلت الحكومة الصينية ، فمن المحتمل أن يكون عبارة عن باندا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the second story that I'd like to tell
القصة الثانية التي أود إخباركم عنها
is, actually starts in my own house.
بدأت حقيقة في منزلي
This is my apartment.
هذه هي شقتي
This is the view from my apartment,
وهذا هو المنظر من شقتي
over the sort of landscape of triangular balconies
من خلال هذا المنظر من الشرفات المثلثة
that our client called the Leonardo DiCaprio balcony.
التي سماها زبوننا شرفة ليوناردو دي كابريو
And they form this sort of vertical backyard
التي تشكل نوعاً من فناء خلفي عمودي الشكل
where, on a nice summer day, you'll actually get introduced to all your neighbors
حيث أنه في يوم صيفي لطيف، ستتمكن من المباشرة على كل الجيران
in a vertical radius of 10 meters.
ضمن دائرة نصف قطرها العمودي عشرة أمتار
The house is sort of a distortion of a square block.
هذا المنزل هو نوع من التشويه للكتلة المربعة
Trying to zigzag it to make sure
بحيث تكون بشكل متعرج للتأكد
that all of the apartments look at the straight views,
من أن كل الشقق تتطلع على نفس المناظر بإستقامة
instead of into each other.
بدلاً من داخل بعضها البعض
Until recently, this was the view from my apartment,
حتى وقت قريب كان هذا هو المنظر من شقتي
onto this place where our client actually bought the neighbor site.
حتى قام زبوننا بشراء المكان المجاور
And he said that he was going to do an apartment block
ومن ثم قال أنه سيقوم ببناء مبنى سكني
next to a parking structure.
بجانب مواقف السيارات
And we thought, rather than doing a traditional stack of apartments
واعتقدنا أنه بدلاً عن بناء حزمة تقليدية من الشقق
looking straight into a big boring block of cars,
تواجه منظراً مملاً لمجموعة من السيارات
why don't we turn all the apartments into penthouses,
لماذا لا نقوم بتحويل جميع الشقق إلى أبنية اضافية
put them on a podium of cars.
ونقوم بوضعها على طبقة فوق السيارات
And because Copenhagen is completely flat,
وبسبب أن كوبنهاغن مسطحة بالكامل
if you want to have a nice south-facing slope with a view,
فإذا أردت ان تحصل على منظر مائل على اتجاه الجنوب
you basically have to do it yourself.
يجب عليك القيام بذلك بنفسك أساساً
Then we sort of cut up the volume,
لذلك قمنا نوعاً ما بتقليص الحجم
so we wouldn't block the view from my apartment.
لذلك لم نحجب المنظر من شقتي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And essentially the parking is sort of occupying the deep space
وبالضرورة أن مواقف السيارات ستحتل المساحة
underneath the apartments.
تحت الشقق
And up in the sun, you have a single layer of apartments
وفي الأعلى في الشمس، لدينا ما يشبه الطبقة الواحدة من الشقق
that combine all the splendors of a suburban lifestyle,
هذا يجمع ما بين كل رونق السكن في الضواحي
like a house with a garden with a sort of metropolitan view,
كمنزل مع حديقة مع منظر حضري
and a sort of dense urban location.
ونوع من الموقع الحضري بشدة
This is our first architectural model.
هذا هو نموذجنا المعماري الأول
This is an aerial photo taken last summer.
هذه صورة التقطت من الجو الصيف الماضي
And essentially, the apartments cover the parking.
وبالضرورة فإن الشقق تغطي مواقف السيارات
They are accessed through this diagonal elevator.
بحيث يمكن الوصول اليها عبر هذا المصعد المائل
It's actually a stand-up product from Switzerland,
هذا في الحقيقة منتج يمثل سويسرا
because in Switzerland they have a natural need for diagonal elevators.
لأنه في سويسرا لديهم حاجة طبيعية للمصاعد المائلة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the facade of the parking,
و واجهة مواقف السيارات
we wanted to make the parking naturally ventilated,
أردنا أن تكون تهوية مواقف السيارات طبيعية
so we needed to perforate it.
لذلك احتجنا لصنع أخرام بها
And we discovered that by controlling the size of the holes,
واكتشفنا انه بالتحكم بحجم الفتحات
we could actually turn the entire facade
فأننا نستطيع تحويل الواجهة بكاملها
into a gigantic, naturally ventilated,
الى صورة عملاقة طبيعية التهوية
rasterized image.
ومنقطة
And since we always refer to the project as The Mountain,
ونظراً لأننا دائماً نشير الى المشروع ب "الجبل"
we commissioned this Japanese Himalaya photographer
فوضنا مصور جبال الهيمالايا الياباني
to give us this beautiful photo of Mount Everest,
ليعطينا هذه الصورة الجميلة لقمة آيفرست
making the entire building a 3,000 square meter artwork.
جاعلاً المبنى بأكمله عبارة عن ثلاثة الآف متر مربع من الأعمال الفنية
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So if you go back into the parking, into the corridors,
فإذا قمت بالعودة الى موقف السيارات ، داخل الأروقة
it's almost like traveling into a parallel universe
فإنك تجدها مشابهة للسفر عبر عالم موازي
from cars and colors,
من السيارات والألوان
into this sort of south-facing urban oasis.
وفي هذا المبنى الذي يشبه نوعاً من الواحة الحضرية المتجهة جنوباً
The wood of your apartment continues outside becoming the facades.
يتواصل الخشب من شقتك ليشكل الواجهة خارجاً
If you go even further, it turns into this green garden.
واذا ذهبت ابعد من ذلك فإنها تتحول الى هذه الحديقة الخضراء
And all the rainwater that drops on the Mountain
وكل مياه الأمطار التي تسقط على "الجبل"
is actually accumulated.
يتم جمعها في الواقع
And there is an automatic irrigation system
وهنالك نظام اوتوماتيكي للري
that makes sure that this sort of landscape of gardens,
يحرص على أن المناظر الطبيعية للحدائق
in one or two years it will sort of transform
ستتحول في غضون عام او إثنين
into a Cambodian temple ruin,
لتصبح كمعبد كمبودي أثري
completely covered in green.
مغطاة بالكامل بالحدائق الخضراء
So, the Mountain is like our first built example
إذاً "الجبل" كان مثالاً لمبنانا الأول
of what we like to refer to as architectural alchemy.
ولما نود أن نشير البه بالخيمياء المعمارية
This idea that you can actually create, if not gold,
هذه الفكرة التي يمكنك فعلاً خلقها إذا لمن تكن ذهباً
then at least added value by mixing
فإنها على الأقل تصبح ذات قيمة عن طريق مزج
traditional ingredients, like normal apartments
المكونات التقليدية ، مثل الشقق العادية
and normal parking,
ومواقف السيارات العادية
and in this case actually offer people
وفي هذه الحالة فإنها توفر حقيقة للناس
the chance that they don't have to choose between
الفرصة لجعلهم لا يضطرون للإختيار ما بين
a life with a garden or a life in the city.
الحياة مع حديقة ، أو الحياة داخل المدينة
They can actually have both.
حيث يمكنهم الحصول على الاثنين في الحقيقة
As an architect, it's really hard to set the agenda.
كمعماري، فإنه من الصعب وضع جدول للأعمال
You can't just say that now I'd like to do a sustainable city
لا يمكنك أن تقول ببساطة أنك تود بناء مدينة مستدامة
in central Asia,
في آسيا الوسطى
because that's not really how you get commissions.
لأن ذلك ليست الطريقة التي تحصل بها على الصفقات
You always have to sort of adapt and improvise
يجب عليك دائماً أن تطور وتكيّف
to the opportunities and accidents that happen,
للفرص والحوادث التي تقع
and the sort of turmoil of the world.
ونوعاً من فوضى العالم
One last example is that recently we,
مثال واحد أخير نقوم به حالياً
like last summer, we won the competition
حيث فزنا الصيف الماضي بمناقصة
to design a Nordic national bank.
للمصرف الوطني لبلدان الشمال الأوربي
This was the director of the bank when he was still smiling.
وهذا كان مدير البنك عندما كان لا يزال يبتسم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was in the middle of the capital so we were really excited by this opportunity.
كان في وسط العاصمة لذلك كنا فعلاً متحمسين للفرصة
Unfortunately, it was the national bank of Iceland.
لسوء الحظ كان المصرف الوطني الآيسلندي
At the same time, we actually had a visitor --
في نفس الوقت كان لدينا زائر
a minister from Azerbaijan came to our office.
وزير من اذربيجان قدم لمكتبنا
We took him to see the Mountain. And he got very excited
واخذناه لرؤية "الجبل" وتحمس كثيراً
by this idea that you could actually make mountains
بهذه الفكرة يمكنك فعلاً صنع جبال
out of architecture,
خارجاً عن العمارة
because Azerbaijan is known as the Alps of Central Asia.
لأن أذربيجان تمثل جبال الألب لآسيا الوسطى
So he asked us if we could actually imagine
فقام بسؤالنا إذا كنا قادرين علي تصور
an urban master plan
خطة للتطوير الحضري
on an island outside the capital
على جزيرة خارج العاصمة
that would recreate the silhouette of the seven most significant mountains
لإعادة بناء نسخة مطابقة للجبال السبعة المعروفة
of Azerbaijan.
في أذربيجان
So we took the commission.
قبلنا المهمة
And we made this small movie that I'd like to show.
وصنعنا هذا الفيلم الصغير الذي أود عرضه عليكم
We quite often make little movies.
نحن غالباً ما نصنع أفلام قليلة
We always argue a lot about the soundtrack,
ودائماً ما نتجادل حول الموسيقى التصويرية
but in this case it was really easy to choose the song.
لكن في هذه الحالة كان من السهل حقيقية اختيار الموسيقى
So basically, Baku is this sort of crescent bay
حيث أن باكو عاصمة أذربيجان نوعاً ما هي عبارة عن خليج على شكل هلال أساساً
overlooking the island of Zira, the island that we are planning --
تطل على جزيرة زيرا حيث نقوم بالبناء
almost like the diagram of their flag.
تقريباً مثل الرسم التخطيطي لعلمها
And our main idea was
وفكرتنا العامة كانت
to sort of sample the seven most significant mountains
تمثيل الجبال السبعة المشهورة
of the topography of Azerbaijan
في طبوغرافيا أذربيجان
and reinterpret them into urban and architectural structures,
واعادة وضعها في هياكل معمارية وحضرية
inhabitable of human life.
كمأوى لحياة البشر
Then we place these mountains on the island,
ومن ثم وضعنا هذي الجبال على الجزيرة
surrounding this sort of central green valley,
تحيط بهذا النوع من الوادي الأخضر المركزي
almost like a central park.
كحديقة مركزية تقريباً
And what makes it interesting is that the island right now
وما يجعل الموضوع حماسياً أن الجزيرة الآن
is just a piece of desert. It has no vegetation.
عبارة عن قطعة من الصحراء ، بلا أي غطاء نباتي
It has no water. It has no energy, no resources.
وبلا ماء ، بلا طاقة وبلا مصادر
So we actually sort of designed the entire island as a single ecosystem,
ذلك قمنا بتصميم الجزيرة كنظام بيئي موحد
exploiting wind energy to drive the desalination plants,
يستخدم طاقة الرياح لتشغيل محطات تحلية المياه
and to use the thermal properties of water
ويستخدم الخصائص الحرارية للماء
to heat and cool the buildings.
لتسخين وتبريد المباني
And all the sort of excess freshwater wastewater
وكل فائض المياه العذبة ومياه الصرف الصحي
is filtered organically into the landscape,
تتم تنقيتها عضوياً في المنظر الطبيعي
gradually transforming the desert island
تدريجياً تحول الجزيرة الصحراوية
into sort of a green, lush landscape.
لمناظر خضراء خصبة
So, you can say where an urban development
لذا وكما يمكنكم أن تروا حيث أن التطوير الحضري
normally happens at the expense of nature,
يحدث دائماً على حساب الطبيعة
in this case it's actually creating nature.
اما في هذه الحالة فأنه يقوم بصنعها
And the buildings, they don't only sort of
والمباني ليست فقط عبارة
invoke the imagery of the mountains,
أخذ لصور الجبال
they also operate like mountains.
بل فعلاً تتصرف مثلها
They create shelter from the wind.
حيث تمثل حاجزاً من الريح
They accumulate the solar energy.
وتجمع الطاقة الشمسية
They accumulate the water.
وتقوم بجمع المياه
So they actually transform the entire island
وبذلك يتم تحويل الجزيرة
into a single ecosystem.
الى نظام بيئي موحد
So we recently presented the master plan,
لذلك قمنا مؤخراً بعرض الخطة الرئيسية
and it has gotten approved.
وقد تمت الموافقة عليها
And this summer we are starting the construction documents
وهذا الصيف سنبدأ وثائق التشييد والبناء
of the two first mountains,
لأول جبلين
in what's going to be the first carbon-neutral island
فيما ستصبح أول جزيرة خالية من الكربون
in Central Asia.
في آسيا الوسطى
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Yes, maybe just to round off.
نعم ، ربما بمجرد جولة
So in a way you can see how the Mountain in Copenhagen
لذلك يمكنك بطريقة ما أن ترى كيف أن الجبل في كوبنهاغن
sort of evolved into the Seven Peaks of Azerbaijan.
نوع من التطور للقمم السبعة في أذربيجان
With a little luck and some more evolution,
وبقليل من الحظ ومزيد من التطور
maybe in 10 years it could be the Five Mountains on Mars.
ربما تصبح الجبال الخمسة على سطح المريخ في خلال عشرة أعوام
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)